Taft, Philip Papers 5541
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Wayne State University - Dr. Philip P. Mason, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Correspondence re Taft's depositing material in the Archives
  - We, 1950-1975 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - WGBH Project - Elsa Rassbach, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Correspondence re series of television programs on American labor history for which Taft served as an historical consultant; includes the agreement between WGBH and Taft, "Draft Report on the Planning Conferences of the American Labor History Series," 26 pages; 30 page untitled manuscript
  - Wh-Wr, 1960-1976 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Y, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Correspondence with Irwin Yellowitz re Yellowitz's promotion and fellowship application
- Series II. Research/Subject Files
  - Actors, 1896-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Agricultural Workers, 1933-1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Air - Transportation, Freedom of the, 1931-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Six page statement by Edward F. McGrady, representing the American Federation of Labor (AFL), before Congressional committee, opposing award of mail carrier contract to Century Air Line. Includes table comparing pilots' hours and wages among air mail carriers (c. 1931). "Freedom of Air," 4 page statement, adopted May 4, 1945, by AFL Executive Council and sent to Senate Foreign Relations Committee, opposing executive agreements re foreign airlines
  - Air Line Pilots, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Aluminum Workers, 1934-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes vituperative correspondence between officials of Aluminum Workers Union and AFL
  - American Alliance for Labor and Democracy, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    List of Officers and Executive Council, including Samuel Gompers, President; 4 page manuscript re formation of Alliance (C. 1917); "Outline of Plans of the American Alliance for Labor and Democracy," 6 page document, pages 3 and 4 missing; 3 page minutes of conference, July 27, 1917; 7 page account of a meeting with unemployed Cloakmakers, December 12, 1917; form letter; miscellaneous notes re the Alliance
  - American Federation of Labor (AFL) - Assessments, 1880-1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Notes; form letters
  - American Federation of Labor - Beginnings - Early Organizations, 1891-1925 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    "An Introduction and Over All View," n.d., 16 pages; "Journal of Proceedings," 1901, 14 pages; letter to Central Federated Union (from Gompers?), December 31, 1902, 2 pages
  - American Federation of Labor - Building Trades Department Documents, 1911-1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Manuscript "Labor in the Construction Industry," n.d., 26 pages; defense agreement between Building and Construction Trades Department and U.S. government, July 22, 1941, 4 pages
  - American Federation of Labor - Building Trades Department - Notes, 1900-1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    "Building Trades," fragmented rough draft of manuscript, probably by Taft.
  - American Federation of Labor-CIO, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    AFL-CIO Platform Statement, in Daily Labor Report, August 10, 1956, 10 pages; "Fact Sheet for AFL-CIO Fifth Constitutional Convention," November 11, 1963, 4 pages; AFL-CIO press releases re Convention statements, November 12, 13 and 14, 1963
  - American Federation of Labor - Conventions: Actions of Delegates, 1872-1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Copious typed and handwritten notes, mostly from 1881-1891, on meetings and correspondence re Knights of Labor, Gompers
  - American Federation of Labor - Conventions: Actions of Delegates, 1874-1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Departments, 1898-1938 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Labor - Departments - See also under department name. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Labor - Executive Council, 1909-1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Eight page Policy Statement, 7/15/49; correspondence and miscellaneous notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Federal Labor Unions, 1919-1948 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    "Federal Labor Union Brief As Approved by the Federal Labor Union Conference of the Wisconsin State Federation of Labor," May 1, 1948, 7 pages; notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Financial, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Taft's cancelled checks and receipts
  - American Federation of Labor - Income and Per Capita, 1879-1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Form letter, May 4, 1937, 2 pages; miscellaneous notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Industrial/Dual Unionism, 1903-1923 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - American Federation of Labor - Industrial/Dual Unionism (Box 3, Folder 19)
    See also: Committee for Industrial Organization, Box 4.
  - American Federation of Labor - Maritime Trades Department, 1919-1957 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    "A Brief History of the Maritime Trades Department, AFL-CIO," 1957, 16 pages; statement by AFL representative to House Committee of Merchant Marine and Fisheries, opposing the creation of a Merchant Marine Service for training in war, June 23, 1949, 2 pages. See also: Maritime folders, Box 8
  - American Federation of Labor - May Day, Labor Day, 1882-1902 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - American Federation of Labor - Membership, 1885-1942 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - American Federation of Labor - Metal Trades Department, 1900-1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - American Federation of Labor - No-Raiding Agreements, 1942-1954 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Correspondence, notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Organizers, 1884-1953 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    "The Organization Plan of the AFL," 9 page address by Frank P. Fenton, Director of Organization, AFL, to the National Broadcasting Company, February 5, 1940; form letter, January 2, 1936, 4 pages; miscellaneous notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Public Relations Programs, 1937-1948 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    "A Public Relations and Advertising Program for the AFL: Tentative Suggestions and Recommendations," by Owen and Chappell, Inc., n.d. 13 pages; public relations budget, n.d.; form letter; notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Railway Employees Department, 1892-1958 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Statement by George M. Harrison, Grand President of the Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees, and also representing 20 other railway unions, before a Senate Committee hearing, opposing a proposed amendment to the Railway Labor Act which would outlaw strikes, June 5, 1950, 24 pages; statement by Michael Fox, President of the Railway Employees' Department, AFL-CIO, and also Vice-Chairman of the Railway Labor Executives' Association, before a Senate sub-committee, urging that any federal financial relief to rail carriers be tied to the curtailment of contracting-out for equipment maintenance, April 2, 1958, 16 pages; correspondence; notes
  - American Federation of Labor - Reconstruction Program, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    "AFL Reconstruction Program," 1918, 16 pages; "Report of the Committee on Reconstruction of the AFL," January 1, 1919, 6 pages; notes
  - American Federation of Labor - State Federations of Labor, 1864-1924 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Reprint, incomplete "History of the NYS Federation of Labor," n.d., 8 pages; reprint re Illinois State Federation of Labor, n.d., 6 pages; note chiefly re Illinois State Federation of Labor; reprint, Digest of Labor Laws re New York State Federation of Labor, n.d., 9 pages
  - American Federation of Labor - Vote Books (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Vote books 3-28, January 1, 1898-October 14, 1924; report of AFL Executive Council votes, August 20, 1919-December 28, 1920, 41 pages; reprint (incomplete) re early history of AFL-Knights of Labor resolutions
  - Annexation, Hawaii and the Philippines, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Anti-Labor Court Cases, 1840-1921 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Anti-Labor Legislation (except Taft-Hartley), 1933-1952 (Box 3, Folder 33-33a)
    Statements before Congress, form letters, correspondence, press releases, and notes re various bills, especially "Case", "Hobbs", and "Smith".
  - Anti-Labor Organization and Movements, 1901-1915 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Anti-Labor Practices, 1865-1947 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Arbitration (Compulsory), 1882-1941 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    "Statement on Compulsory Arbitration by President Gompers, December 13, 1921," 6 pages; "Compulsory Arbitration," by Samuel Gompers, 5 pages, n.d.; form letter to U.S. Representatives opposing compulsory arbitration, from AFL President Green and Secretary-Treasurer George Meany, June 20, 1941; notes
  - Automation, 1887-1963 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    "The Impact of Technological Change," Upjohn Institute for Employment Research, September 1963; Letter to AFL President Green from AFL legislative representative re providing for workers displaced by machinery; notes
  - Armaments - Conference of Limitation of, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Letter from State Department to Samuel Gompers appointing him to Advisory Committee of U.S. representatives to the conference; Cablegram; notes
  - Automobile Workers (UAW) - Letters, Notes, etc., 1911-1964 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    "The United Automobile Workers: Past, Present and Future," by Walter Reuther, President, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America, Virginia Law Review, 1964, 45 pages; "The United Auto Workers Union," n.d., 9 pages; "Organization of the Automobile Workers," n.d., 2 pages; "Wage Rates Prevailing as of January 1934, on Various Operations in the Automobile Industry," showing difference between rates for men and women, 5 pages; "Wage Chronology #5: Chrysler Corp., 1939048," 3 pages; correspondence between President Roosevelt and AFL President Green, re industrial code of fair practice for the auto industry, November 1934; correspondence and form letters re strikes and disputes with CIO
  - Automobile Workers - Mansfield Strike, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    General Motors National Conference, emergency session re wildcat strike at Mansfield Fisher Body plant, March 9, 1967, 134 pages; "Proceedings of Special Session, International Executive Board, UAW: Show Cause Hearing," February 22, 1967, 69 pages; press releases; clippings
  - Automobile Workers - Newspaper Clippings, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Automobile Workers - Notes, 1920-1955 (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
    "The United Automobile Workers of America," n.d., 2 pages; "Confidential" internal memo of United Mine Workers (Vice-President Philip Murray to John L. Lewis) re dissention within the Auto Workers' Union, December 13, 1938, 3 pages
  - Automobile Workers - Report of the Labor Board, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    "Strictly Confidential" Final Report of the Automobile Labor Board, 45 pages
  - Bakery and Confectionery Workers, 1880-1959 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Bakery and Confectionery Workers - Corruption, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    "Report of the Ethical Practices Committee to the AFL-CIO Executive Council" re charges of corruption within the Bakery union, September 16, 1957, 53 pages; form letters from the Committee to Preserve Integrity in the Bakery and Confectionery Workers International Union, and from the General Executive Board of the union; resolutions by the AFL-CIO Executive Council re the Bakery union; copy of legal injunction, n.d. 12 pages
  - Banks, Labor, 1922-1932 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Barbers, 1887-1938 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Correspondence between Barbers' union President and AFL President re revocation of charter arising from jurisdictional dispute with CIO and United Mine Workers
  - Baseball Players' Fraternity - Application for Charter (1917), 1900-1918 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Notes include comment by Gompers, opposing placement of baseball as non-essential industry in wartime
  - Bill - Labor's Bill of Grievances (1906), 1906-1920 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Blacksmiths, 1889-1894 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Boilermakers and Iron Shipbuilders of America, 1881-1936 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Letter from AFL President re CIO, December 3, 1936, 2 pages; notes
  - Boot Makers, 1887-1952 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    9 page manuscript re history of bootmakers, n.d.; letter from AFL President re CIO raiding, November 1, 1941, 1 page; notes
  - Boycotts, 1887-1937 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Form letter form AFL President, January 18, 1937, 2 pages; notes
  - Brewery Workers, 1888-1941 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    9 page manuscript re history of brewery workers, n.d.; reprint, "National Union of the United Brewery Workmen of the U.S.," n.d., 2 pages; notes
  - Bricklayers, 1871-1953 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    11 page manuscript re history of bricklayers, 1953; notes
  - Broadcasters, National Association, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Three booklets by National Association of Broadcasters ("Confidential: For Use of Station Management Only"): "When You First Face Unionization," 22 pages; "Working With Unions," 8 pages; "Labor Relations in Small Stations," 11 pages
  - Brookwood Labor College, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Several letters from various affiliated union officials, protesting AFL Executive Council's directive, made without a hearing, to withhold financial support of Brookwood following charges of Communist and anti-AFL leanings; printed reply by AFL President Green, 6 pages; notes
  - Canadian Labor Organization - "One Big Union", 1919-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Correspondence; financial statement, 1920-21; notes
  - Car Builders Union, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Carpenters, 1888-1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Eight page manuscript re history of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, c. 1951; notes; correspondence. See also: Landis Award, Box 7, File Folder 44-46
  - Carriage and Wagon Workers, 1891-1912 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cement Workers, 1904-1912 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Child Labor, 1889-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Status report of state-by-state ratification of Child Labor Amendment, January 29, 1934; correspondence; press releases; notes
  - Christian Unions, 1872-1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Issues of The Labor Leader, October 31, 1941 and September 15, 1951; Information Service of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, November 23, 1946; notes
  - Cigarmakers, 1864-1884 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Civil Service Commission, U.S., 1937-1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    AFL resolution, sent to Senators and Congressmen, supporting Civil Service Commission, November 15, 1937; Executive Order by President John F. Kennedy authorizing an appeals procedure within the Civil Service System
  - Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC), 1933-1942 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Original bill, plus attached amendments, setting up CCC, March 21, 1933; notes and correspondence re AFL opposition to CCC; statement by AFL representative before Senate subcommittee supporting continuation of CCC, 1942
  - Cleaners (Retail), Dryers and Pressers (Box 4, Folder 11)
    n.d. routine
  - Closed Shop (Union Shop), 1907 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Clothing Workers, 1887-1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Fourteen page manuscript re "Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America," c. 1951; notes
  - Committee for Industrial Organization, 1933-1935 (Box 4, Folder 14-14a)
    "The Origin and Program of the Committee for Industrial Organization," 6 page manuscript, n.d.; "National and International Unions Voting for the Minority Report on Industrial Unionism at the 1935 AF of L Convention," 2 page list; "Minutes of Meeting of Committee for Industrial Organization," November 9, 1935, 3 pages; correspondence between AFL President William Green and CIO Chairman John L. Lewis; other routine correspondence; notes. See also: AFL -Industrial/Dual Unionism, Box 3, File Folder 19.
  - Committee for Industrial Organization, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    "Declaration and Resolution on Committee for Industrial Organization," 10 page statement by the United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers Calling for representation of CIO-affiliated unions at AFL convention and for unity, October 8, 1936; "Resolution" by AFL Executive Council, ordering CIO-affiliated unions to choose between the CIO and the AFL, August 5, 1936; notes
  - Committee for Industrial Organization, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    "Extract From Minutes of Executive Council Meeting," January 15-29, 1936, 3 pages, AFL calls for dissolution of CIO (also sent as press release and form letter); "Summary of Meeting Between CIO and Sub-Committee of the AFL Executive Council," May 19, 1936, 2 pages; "Study of Recently-Organized Locals" from CIO (pencil notation: June 1936 CIO under signature of Brojchy sent this questionnaire to Federal and recently organized unions), 2 pages; fifteen page legal opinion re AFL suspension of CIO-affiliated unions, addressed to AFL President Green, May 1, 1936; notes
  - Committee for Industrial Organization, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Letters between AFL and CIO-affiliated unions
  - Communications Association, America (Box 4, Folder 18)
    "Communications Workers," 7 page manuscript, n.d.; letter to Gompers from Commercial Telegraphers' Union of America, 3 pages, July 28, 1917; notes
  - Communist Party Minutes, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Also includes membership list with "C.I.O. Connection," n.d., 4 pages
  - Communists - CIO infiltration, 1933-1953 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Sex reports by CIO Executive Board Committee recommending that the CIO Executive Board revoke the certificate of affiliation with the following unions whose policies and activities were judged to be "directed toward the achievement of the program ... of the Communist Party rather than ... the CIO Constitution" [c. 1950]: the International Fur and Leather Workers Union; The National Union of Marine Cooks and Stewards; the United Office and Professional Workers of America; the Food, Tobacco, Agricultural and Allied Workers of America; the International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers; and the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU)
  - Communists - Documents, 1925-1950 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    "Confidential Report on Communists and Communist Activities Within the Trade Union Movement, submitted to President Green, February 11, 1935," 24 pages; statement by AFL representative before Senate Judiciary Committee, opposing Mundt-Nixon Bill, May 28, 1948, 14 pages; statement by AFL President Green before the House Committee on Un-American Activities opposing Sheppard and Raskin bills, outlawing Communist Party, March 25, 1947, 5 pages; correspondence, resolution re Bookkeepers and Stenographers Union, May 1937; statement by AFL representative before House Committee on Un-American Activities, opposing Mundt-Nixon Bill, March 24, 1950, 5 pages; "Special Report: Communists in Labor Unions," prepared for members of the Research Institute of America, April 4, 1946, 16 pages; form letters
  - Communists - Notes, 1928-1951 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Confederated Unions of America, 1946-1956 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations - Formation of, 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    "Report of Director" to CIO meeting, January 9, 1936, 4 pages and March 9, 1937, 5 pages; notes
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations - General, 1917-1955 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Several letters from AFL President to CIO President re CIO raiding on AFL unions, 1942-45; press release and form letter stating CIO position on various anti-labor bills, 1940; press release stating CIO opposition to third party in U.S. Presidential election of 1948; telegram reporting decision by United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Jointers to remain affiliated with AFL, September 8, 1955; notes. See also: Machinists, Box 8; Newspaper Guild, Box 9, File Folder 26; Steel, Box 10; and Teamsters, Box 13.
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations - AFL Controversy with Lewis and the Miners' Union, 1936-1949 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Correspondence; notes; press release announcing AFL President Green's resignation from United Mine Workers, 1938
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    "Memorandum on Essential Conditions for Unity," unsigned, probably by AFL, with hand notation "1937", 6 pages; form letters; correspondence; notes
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Form letters, correspondence, notes
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Correspondence from AFL President Green to various union officials; correspondence between AFL President Green and various officials re CIO participation and AFL's refusal to participate in the National Labor Congress in Cuba, January 1939; notes
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations - Peace Negotiations with AFL, 1936-1943 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Press clippings; correspondence; form letters; notes
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations - Peace Negotiations with AFL, 1938-1955 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    "Memorandum on the Basis for Peace Negotiations between the AFL and the CIO," March 1939, 23 pages; letter to AFL President Green from AFL Vice-President David Dubinsky, advising that unity overture from CIO was a Communist plot, December 10, 1946; telegram (copy) to President Roosevelt from AFL President Green, expressing willingness to negotiate with CIO, n.d., 2 pages; "Statement by the Executive Council of the AFL," calling on President Roosevelt to publicly blame CIO President John L. Lewis as solely responsible for holding up the peace negotiations, February 8, 1940; correspondence between AFL President Green and CIO President Murray, 1942; "Report and Recommendations of the Joint AFL-CIO Unity Committee," February 9, 1955, 8 pages; miscellaneous correspondence, press releases, form letters, and notes
  - Conscription - Military, Civilian Manpower, 1925-1950 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    "AFL Supports Voluntary Manpower Control," 4 page excerpt from Executive Council minutes, February 5, 1945; statement by AFL representative before Senate committee, opposing peacetime military conscription, June 5, 1950, 4 pages; form letters; notes
  - Convict Labor, 1885-1946 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    "Convict Labor," by AFL President Green, n.d., 3 pages; "Convict Labor," December 31, 1930, 4 pages; "Convict Labor Legislation in the States," n.d. 3 pages; "Labelling Prison-Made Goods," August 5, 1927, 2 pages; "Action Taken by AFL on Paying of Compensation to Inmates of Penal Institutions," covering AFL positions on convict labor 1893-1922, 2 pages; "Annual Report, Board of Directors, Federal Prison Industries, Inc., Fiscal Year 1946," 10 pages; ten page manuscript re convict labor, November 7, 1929; form letters; correspondence; notes
  - Coopers' Union, 1872-1899 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Core Makers, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Curriers, 1863-1864 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Defense Production Act, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Demobilization, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Depression's Effect on AFL Income, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Directors Guild of America, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Economy, 1962-1971 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    "Statement on the President's Economic Report ... by Walter P. Reuther, Vice- President, AFL-CIO; Chairman of the AFL-CIO Economic Policy Committee, and President, UAW," February 7, 1962, re technological change, 3 pages (incomplete); "Report of the Economic Policy Committee to the AFL-CIO on The National Economy ... on The Wage Guideline," February 27, 1966, 3 pages; transcript of address by AFL-CIO President George Meany at the International Longshoremen's Association, re state of the national economy, July 19, 1971; brochure, "Labor Looks at Capitalism," by George Meany, December 1966, address to the National Industrial Conference Board
  - Education, 1888-1952 (Box 4, Folder 42)